DAN KLEIN: All right.
Let's see why A star tree search
will be optimal with
an admissible heuristic.
So here's the setup.
Let's say A is an optimal goal node,
and B is a suboptimal goal node.
And let's imagine that h is
an admissible heuristic.
The claim we're going to show is that
A, the optimal node, will exit the
fringe before B, the suboptimal node.
How are we going to show that?
First, let's imagine that
B is on the fringe.
It can't exit the fringe until
it gets on the fringe.
And if B is on the fringe,
the fringe looks
something like This.
So we've already expanded some prefix of
this tree, and we've gotten down to
the point where we've reached
B. Now, some ancestor of A
must be on the fringe.
Maybe it's A itself, but maybe not.
In any case, let's call n the ancestor
of A that's on the fringe.
The claim we're going to show is that
n will be expanded by A star search
before B. If n is expanded before B,
then n's child will be expanded before
B, all the way down to A, and then
eventually A will be expanded before
B.
First, let's look at n versus A. And the
claim is that f of n is less than
or equal to f of A. Why is this?
Let's take a look.
First, what is f of n?
By the definition of f cost for A star,
that's equal to g of n, its path
cost, plus h of n, the heuristic at n.
But we know that h is admissible.
And for an admissible heuristic, h
cannot overestimate the cost to a
closest goal, such as A. That means that
f of n is less than or equal to g
of A, the path cost of A itself.
Because h is zero at a goal, g
of A and f of A are the same.
Putting all this together, we get that
f of n is less than or equal to f of
A.
Next, we'll compare A and B. And we'll
show that f of A is less than f of B.
Why is that true?
Well, we know that g of A, A's
path cost, is less than g
of B, B's path cost.
That's because we assumed that B is
suboptimal, and that's what it means
to be suboptimal.
Again, because h equals zero for an
admissible heuristic at any goal, we
also know that f of A
is less than f of B.
The third thing we have to notice
is that n will expand before
B. Now, why is that?
Well, if we compare n and B, then we'll
see if we put these inequalities
together that f of n is less than or
equal to f of A, which is less than f
of B. And so f of n is
less than f of B.
That means the A star algorithm will
choose to remove n before it moves B
from the queue.
Of course, this holds not only for n,
but for any node along the path
towards A. That means that all ancestors
of A will expand before B.
And in turn, that means A itself will
expand before B. Since we've just
shown that any optimal node will be
removed before any suboptimal node,
that means that A star search is optimal
because the first goal node
that it returns will be optimal.